<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Comparative theology, or, The true and solid grounds of pure and peaceable theology a subject very necessary, tho' hitherto almost wholly neglected : proposed in a university discourse / and now translated from the printed Latin copy, with some few enlargements by the author.</title>
            <author>Garden, James, 1647-1726.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23392</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18782595</idno>
  <idno type="VID">205288</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240876520</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing G219</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">18782595</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23392)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 205288)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1653:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Comparative theology, or, The true and solid grounds of pure and peaceable theology a subject very necessary, tho' hitherto almost wholly neglected : proposed in a university discourse / and now translated from the printed Latin copy, with some few enlargements by the author.</title>
                  <author>Garden, James, 1647-1726.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 102 [i.e. 112] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by the booksellers of London, and Westminister,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Garden by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Errors in paging: p. 13 and 112 misnumbered 31 and 102.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:205288:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205288:1"/>
            <p>COMPARATIVE THEOLOGY; Or, The True and Solid Grounds OF Pure and Peaceable <hi>THEOLOGY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Subject very Necessary, tho' hitherto almost wholly neglected.</p>
            <p>Proposed in an University DISCOURSE.</p>
            <p>And now Translated from the Printed <hi>Latin</hi> Copy, with some few Enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by the Author.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gemmula grata magis quam magno Pondere ferrum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed and Sold by the Booksellers of <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>Westminster.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:205288:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205288:2"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>AN Introduction, with the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion and Design of the whole. Page</hi> 1</item>
               <item>SECT. 1 <hi>Wherein Comparative Theology is handled in a general way. The State wherein Man was created. Man's Duty in that State. The reason of the Prohibition con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil. The Fall of Man occasioned the Enlargement of Religion. A general Idea of this Theology. p:</hi> 11</item>
               <item>SECT. 2. <hi>Wherein this Theology is more distinctly and particularly explain'd. A Scheme of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
<pb facs="tcp:205288:3"/>Religion, shewing the Weight and Import of all the Parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Two particulars in it Worthy of Observation. p.</hi> 22</item>
               <item>SECT. 3. <hi>Wherein several ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Propositions and Corollaries are deduced from the preceding Aecounts of this Theologie. How to discern betwixt the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Principles of Religion, and those that are not such; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt damnable, dangerous, and harmless Errors. p.</hi> 61</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Concl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sion. Wherein the use o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this Theology is more particularly declared. The I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>onveniences to which they are exposed, who are not acquainted with it. The Character of one who follows its direction. The Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue. p.</hi> 93</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:205288:3"/>
            <head>THE PUBLISHER of the TRANSLATION TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Wisdom that's from above is first Pure, then Peaceable:</hi> How for the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian World is at this day from these divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Qualities is but too visible. Men have so transform'd t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Christian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine by their Glosses, as it is now hardly to be found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them in its Truth and
<pb facs="tcp:205288:4"/>Simplicity. The Doctrine of Jesus Christ, as it is deliver'd unto us by his Apostles, is not now to be considered as the Standard of Christianity, so much as the <hi>Shorter and Larger Catechisms, the West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster Confession, the Trent Creed and Canons,</hi> &amp;c. In de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of which, Men relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quish and reject the true Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Essence of Christiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Love of God, and their Neighbours; and frame to themselves such a Doctrine as will flatter their corrupt Nature, and foster their Pride and Envy. In some Nations it has been the great Idol of differing Families and Tribes,
<pb facs="tcp:205288:4"/>to keep up their Feuds and Enmities among themselves, and to prosecute them to the last Extremities in the mutual destruction of one another: Such a bloody and irreconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable Disposition, tho' it has been justly esteem'd Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in them, is yet look'd upon to be a gracious and a holy Zeal in the several Tribes and Parties of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, every one contending so earnestly, and disputing with such Heat and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, that they may main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their own Sect and Sett of Opinions in opposition to all others. And the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of the Respective Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual
<pb facs="tcp:205288:5"/>Heads and Guides, are so far from doing their Duty in restraining these Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as they will not hear of any Principles or Proposals that may tend this way, but if any thing be offered that may contribute to sweeten the Minds of Men toward one another, they make it their Business to treat the Proposers as common Enemies, and to give such Characters both of them, and of their Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as may lead the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to abhor them.</p>
            <p>The prejudices which the false Representations of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion do to the true Interest thereof, and to the Souls of
<pb facs="tcp:205288:5"/>Men, are innumerable: and how hurtful they are to So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties and Commonwealths, the present as well as former Ages is a sufficient Evidence; the Factions in the State can never find fitter Tools for carrying on their Designs, than those of the Church; who are ready to sacrifice both the Liberties and Wealth of their Country, with the Life of Religion it self, to the little Interests of their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: so as we are all concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both as we are Men, and as we are Christians in this our Day to know the things that belong to our Peace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be hid from our Eyes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:205288:6"/>
            <p>The following Discourse was originally intended by the Author to form in the Minds of those Youth, whom he was to train up in Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Studies, such just and adequate Notions of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all its parts, as might raise their Concern for those things in it that are absolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Necessary and Essential; and preserve them from a blind, ungovernable, and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Zeal for those other things, which are either merely circumstantial, or at least not necessary, nor of the Essence thereof, altho' they are now become the Pillar and Ground of most, if not of all
<pb facs="tcp:205288:6"/>the unhappy and unaccount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Contentions that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the Christian world. And a written Copy thereof falling into the hands of some Persons, for whose Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Author has a Great Esteem, they obtain'd his Permission to make it publick: Seeing some Persons have been ready since the Publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, to give ill Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressions of it, unto those who do not understand the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue, it has been thought fit to publish it in <hi>English,</hi> that such might per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>use it with their own, and not with other Men's Eyes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:205288:7"/>
            <p>The few Enlargements that have been made in this Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation are plac'd between Crotchets [] so that they will be easily diseern'd by the Reader. That this Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course may by the Blessing of God, contribute to lead Men to the true Knowledge and Love of God, in Christ Jesus, and to mutual Peace and Charity with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is the earnest Prayer both of the Author and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blisher.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:205288:7"/>
            <head>THE Publisher of the Original in <hi>LATIN</hi> TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Christian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere be many who have written of <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute Theology,</hi> and that oftimes to li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tle purpose, but I have never hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore met with any who
<pb facs="tcp:205288:8"/>have treated of <hi>Compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve Theologie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When by chance I happen'd first to read this Discourse, it did appear to me so Excellent, the Subject so Necessary, and treated withal in that Saving Way which is not common, that I thought the making of it publick, would be a good Office done to all, who aspire after solid Knowledge in Christianity and Divine things.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:205288:8"/>
            <p>If you desire to know the Author, the Disser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation it self does plainly shew, that he has for some time been the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structor of Students in Theology in some Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity: To know more of him, is not necessary, it may be, not expedient, while there are such Heats among the several Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Christians. In the mean time, it were to be wish'd, that those who have the Charge of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb facs="tcp:205288:9"/>to instruct them in divine things, would sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son them with the like Doctrine, then should we see Christian Churches and Common-Wealths, and every private Person also grow and advance daily in all Good, and in Peace and Favour with God and Man: which may our infinitely good God grant, to whom be Glory for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:205288:9"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE Concerning COMPARATIVE THEOLOGY. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>[The Introduction. The ground of the Distinction of Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie into Absolute and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative. Both are describ'd. Inconveniencies arising from the Ignorance of Compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Theologie. The Heads of the following Discourse.]</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>§. 1. ALtho' all the Parts of the Christian Religion do agree
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:205288:10"/>in this, that they are revealed and enjoin'd by God; and also, that they are directed to the Glory of God, and the Salvation of Men; yet they are not all of the same Weight and Importance: but being weigh'd in the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of a Sound Judgment, some of them are found to be more weighty than others. The Prophets tell us, that <hi>Mercy, the Knowledge of God,</hi> and <hi>Obedience to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,</hi> are more acceptable to him than <hi>Sacrifices and Burnt-Offerings,</hi> 1 Sam. 15, 22. Hos. 6, 6. and our blessed Lord calls <hi>Judgment, Mercy and Truth,</hi> compar'd with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:205288:10"/>
               <hi>Tythes of Mint, Cummin and Anise,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>more weighty things of the Law.</hi> Matth. 23, 23. From this Consideration there ariseth a Distinction or Division of that <hi>Skill, Knowledge and Ʋn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding</hi> which is conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sant about Religion, and which is commonly call'd <hi>Theologie,</hi> or <hi>Divinity,</hi> into <hi>Absolute,</hi> and <hi>Respective</hi> or <hi>Comparative. Absolute Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> or that Knowledge of Religion which I call abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, considers its Object only as revealed and enjoined, or instituted by God, and its business is to find out those things which are proposed to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:205288:11"/>us in the Scriptures to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd or practis'd, and to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern and distinguish them from all others. Again, <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative Theologie,</hi> or the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spective Knowledge of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ponders the weight or importance, and observes the Order, Respect and Relation of things belonging to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; whether they be points of Doctrine, or Precepts, or sacred Rites, and teaches to distinguish and put a differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between the <hi>Accessories</hi> of Religion, and the <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pals;</hi> the <hi>Circumstantials</hi> and <hi>Substantials;</hi> the <hi>Means</hi> and their <hi>Ends.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:205288:11"/>
            <p>§. 2. In a preliminary Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course to our Divinity Lectures of the last Year, speaking of the Differences about the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religion, that are in the Christian Church, I touch'd this Distinction by the by; and among the proper Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies of this Evil, I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd the Doctrine of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative Theologie.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the oftner I reflect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the more narrowly I consider this Matter, I am the more convinc'd, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd in my Opinion, of the great Usefulness and Neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssity of this Doctrine. Nor do I much question but you, <hi>my Friends,</hi> will be easily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:205288:12"/>to be of my Mind, when you shall perceive that the corrupt and dangerous State of the Christian Church at present, is in a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree owing to the want of this <hi>Comparative knowledge of Religion,</hi> or of a due regard had to it. For, that among all Sects and Parties of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, true Piety is neglected, and divine Charity and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly Love are waxed cold; that they are cold and remiss in rooting out the Lusts and deprav'd Affections of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Nature; when in the mean time, they lay themselves out with Zeal and applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the propagating some
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:205288:12"/>Opinions that be either ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>scure or uncertain, but no ways necessary, and for the suppressing others of the same Nature which are not hurtful; that some Religious Rites and Ceremonies are pertinaceously retain'd by some Christians, and as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinately rejected by others; that they are at peace with Vice and vicious Persons, while they wage a Cruel War with Error and erring Persons. These things are not so much to be imputed to the want of an <hi>Absolute Knowledge</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as of that which is <hi>Comparative.</hi> No more can
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:205288:13"/>this be attributed to their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ignorant of any Christian Precept, or of any absolute Divine Truth that is of any import to Salvation: But 'tis because the Generality of Christians either do not know, or will not consider how much <hi>Repentance, Self-denial, Mortifying of the Flesh, Charity, Humility,</hi> &amp;c. are of more weight than <hi>Orthodoxy</hi> or a <hi>Sound Belief;</hi> and <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Vice</hi> more hateful than <hi>Error:</hi> The <hi>Essential Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> of Religion excepted in both Cases. Since then the use of <hi>Comparative Theologie</hi> is of so large extent, both for ordering the Lives and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:205288:13"/>of private Christians a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and for settling the publick Affairs which concern the Peace of the Churches within themselves, and their mutual Concord with one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: I presume then, dear Fellow Students, it will be a good Office done to you, and nothing disagreeable to the rest of my Hearers, if I shall furnish you with a Key, by which you may enter into the most remote and intricate Recesses of this so often com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended Theology.</p>
            <p>§. 3. That I may avoid ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling to and agen without Order or Method in this Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, I shall comprise what I
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:205288:14"/>have to say under three Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral heads. (1) I shall give a rude Draught and general Idea of this <hi>Theologie.</hi> (2) I shall descend to a more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular description of it. And in the third place, I shall lay down some Conclusions or Positions, which do natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly flow from this Doctrine of <hi>Comparative Theologie,</hi> and are worthy of your Observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:205288:14"/>
               <head>SECT. 1. </head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>[Wherein Comparative Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie is handled in a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral way. The State wherein Man was Created; Man's Duty in that State. The reason of the Prohibition concerning the Tree of knowledge of Good and Evil. The Fall of Man occasioned the enlargement of Religion A general Idea of this. Theologie.]</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>§. 4. AS to the first, it is to be considered that the <hi>Essence</hi> of Religion, or of the Duty which Man owes to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:205288:15"/>God, or which God requires of Man, in whatsoever State, whether that of Integrity and Innocence, or Restora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion after the Fall, or consum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated Felicity, doth solely consist in the LOVE of GOD, as our Saviour teacheth us, <hi>Matth,</hi> 22, 37. where he says, that the first and greatest Commandment of the Law is to <hi>love the Lord our God with all our Heart, and with all our Soul, with all our Mind, and with all our Strength.</hi> For God being self sufficient, and independent of all other Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, did not in the least stand in need of the Creatures and their Service: but being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:205288:15"/>by a most free, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>constrain'd, and unnecessary Act of his good Pleasure, to take his delight with some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without himself, he did for that end, after the Creation and Fall of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, make Man in his own Image (that is, of a Nature like his own) with whom he might live in Friendship, and have all things in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; by offering Himself, with all His glorious and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable Perfections to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciously enjoyed by Man; and by receiving from him the grateful Return of a Reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procal Love and Affection. And because Man is a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:205288:16"/>made up of a Soul, a spiritual Substance, and a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy which is material: God created this visible and Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real World, and furnished it with innumerable Objects for the delighting the outward Senses, and recreating those Faculties which belong to the Soul, as it is join'd and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Body; and made Man Lord over it. To this end, that as the Soul had God the Infinite Good, fitted and proportioned to its vast Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, so the Body also might not be without suitable and delightful Objects. And to this Design of God in the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the World, the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:205288:16"/>thereof doth excellently agree; wherein we read that this whole Visible World, was at first created and finish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as a Magnificent Palace richly provided with all Kinds of Furniture, and that after this, Man, who was design'd to be its Lord and Master, was made and invested with the Dominion of it.</p>
               <p>§. 5. For so great Favours, so liberally dispens'd unto Man, God required, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expected no other Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony of a grateful Mind but LOVE. And that his Love might be noble and free, generous and unlimited, not necessitated, forced or restrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:205288:17"/>it was the will of God that Man should be at his own disposal, and therefore he endued him with a free Power of determining the Acts and Exercises of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties to these or the other Objects; of adhereing to God by Love or departing from him; and provided he still continued to Love God and to place his delight in him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, nothing was forbidden him: All things were lawful unto him, and he was Master of Power most free (not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a Physical, but also in a Moral Sense) to dispose of all his faculties, and of the Creatures subjected to him at
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:205288:17"/>his Pleasure, and that without any Offence to God. As for the Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil, concerning which the Scriptures inform us, that God charged <hi>Adam</hi> not to Eat of it; this was not done out of Envy, as if God had grudged him that pleasant Fruit (as he was slander'd by the Devil) or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in the least to diminish or infringe the full and free Right and Power which he had bestowed upon him of using his faculties, and all things under his command at his Pleasure, without preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice always of the Love he owed to his Maker. But it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:205288:18"/>is not improbable that God having even then discovered in Man some remote and dawning Dispositions to the Love of the Creatures, did forbid him the use of one Tree; either because his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations to it were greater than was fit, or that by this Symbol he might keep Man mindful that he held all the rest, whereof the free use was allowed to him, by <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Vassalage,</hi> only with a Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon God the Over-Lord of all, to whom on that account, he owed the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Love.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:205288:18"/>
               <p>§ 6. After that Man had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bused the Liberty bestowed upon him, by transferring his Love from God to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and had thereby vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the Law of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and the League of Friendship that was contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with God, and had also lost the Love of God, and with it, the blessed Presence and Company of the Deity who dwelt in his Soul, and fill'd it with Light, and Joy, and Peace; to which suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded Darkness, Anguish and Disquiet: After, I say, that Man had made defection from God, and God was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd to restore Man, then
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:205288:19"/>did the Confines of Religion begin to be enlarged, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the <hi>Love of God</hi> which was lost, and still holds the Principal place among the divine Precepts and Duties of Religion; several other things were revealed, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed, and instituted to be observ'd by Man, as being some of them useful, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers necessary for recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Love of God</hi> that was lost, and for bringing back Man, that was gone astray into the road of his Duty.</p>
               <p>§. 7. Out of what hath been already said, this Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct and <hi>General Idea</hi> of the Doctrine of <hi>Comparative Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:205288:19"/>doth arise, <hi>viz.</hi> In the State of <hi>Nature's Integrity and Innocence,</hi> the <hi>Love of God</hi> made up the whole of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, nor was there any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Duty incumbent on Man, but to <hi>love the Lord his God with all his Heart.</hi> Again in the State of <hi>Nature deprav'd,</hi> and consider'd as it is to be repair'd and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, the same <hi>Love of God</hi> still makes the first, the Chief and Capital part of Religion, which alone is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired for it self, and for whose sake all the other things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Religion are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined: So that the Love of God being compar'd with the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:205288:20"/>remaining parts of Religion, is the end to which they all refer and lead as so many <hi>Ways</hi> and <hi>Means.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>[Wherein this Theologie is more distinctly and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly explain'd. A Scheme of the Christian Religion, shewing the weight and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of all the Parts thereof. Two particulars in it worthy of Observation.]</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>§. 8. FOR a more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular and distinct Explication of this Doctrine of <hi>Comparative Theologie</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:205288:20"/>thus summarily proposed, we are in the next place to shew how, and in what order all the other Precepts and Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of Religion do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect <hi>Charity</hi> or the <hi>Love of God,</hi> and serve for kindling up again that heavenly Flame in the Hearts of Men.</p>
               <p>§. 9. First then, inasmuch as Man had unworthily vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the League of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship into which God had vouchsafed to admit him, and by transferring unto the <hi>Creatures</hi> the Love and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection that is due to <hi>God only,</hi> had drawn upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self God's Displeasure, and exposed himself unto Eternal
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:205288:21"/>Death; 'twas impossible that he could be restored unto his former State, without the <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> of God par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning his Offence on these terms, (and none more easie could be either desired or granted) <hi>viz.</hi> That Man should return to his Duty, that is, to the <hi>Love of God;</hi> and that for this Effect God should allow unto Man a competent Time, together with such Helps as were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary for that purpose.</p>
               <p>§. 10. For obtaining of this Mercy, the <hi>Intercession</hi> of a <hi>Mediator</hi> was necessary; one who might procure this by his <hi>Merit</hi> and <hi>Favour</hi> with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:205288:21"/>God. I shall not make it my Business here to enquire into the Causes and Reasons why God would not be reconcil'd to fall'n Man without the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervention of a Mediator. That he would not, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from this, because for want of a Mediator the fall'n Angels were precluded from any access to the Grace and Favour of God. But the Reason why the Son of God passing by the fall'n Angels undertook the Cause of fall'n Man, seems to be partly the Relation of the same common Nature; <hi>For he took not on him the Nature of Angels, but the Seed of Abraham,</hi> Heb. 2,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:205288:22"/>16. and the vertue and efficacy of his Incarnation, together with what he did and suffer'd in the Flesh, began to take place immediately after Man's Fall, whence our blessed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour is call'd, <hi>The Lamb slain from the beginning of the World.</hi> Rev. 13.8.) partly because the whole Race of Mankind falling in and with their Stock, the Case of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>'s Posterity deserv'd Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miseration, they being made obnoxious unto, and involv'd in everlasting Misery, before they came to exist by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves out of their Seminal Principles, or to enioy the use of their Reason and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:205288:22"/>
               <p>§. 11. To this mean of Salvation which is placed without us, and hath no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence upon us, that which answers on our parts is <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Gratitude</hi> to Jesus Christ, who became our Surety to God; and <hi>Faith,</hi> whereby we ascribe to him those hopes of Salvation that he hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chased for us, and rely on his Merits and Intercession for the pardon of our Sins, the acceptance of our Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with God, and the obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of every thing that is good for us.</p>
               <p>§. 12. Because the <hi>Pardon</hi> which Christ procur'd for fall'n Man is only <hi>Conditional,</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:205288:23"/>and the <hi>Conditions</hi> which God requires of us in order to our being restored to his favour (<hi>viz.</hi> that being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly penitent for our Sins we should return to God and our Duty, restore unto him the full possession of our hearts, and both begin and ever continue to love him with all our Soul) are such as they cannot directly, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, and at once be perform'd by us, because of the thick Clouds of Ignorance and the corrupt Affections wherewith Sin hath sill'd our Minds; therefore some <hi>Means</hi> must of <hi>Necessity</hi> be prescrib'd and made use of for this end,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:205288:23"/>by which, as by Steps, we may gradually ascend to the perfect Love of God, which is seated, as it were, upon the high Throne of Religion. Such means hath God prescri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in his word, and by so do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hath adopted them into the Family of Religion.</p>
               <p>§. 13. 'Tis clear and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in it self, that in return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Love of God</hi> we must take a course quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that by which Man departed from it. Seeing then Man lost this Love of God, not by enjoying of nor taking his divertisement with the Creatures (both which he might lawfully do) but
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:205288:24"/>by uniting his Heart unto them by Love, it follows, that if we would have this Divine fire to descend upon the Altar of our Hearts, we must of necessity <hi>extinguish</hi> and put out the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure and muddy <hi>Love of the World,</hi> and of the <hi>Creatures:</hi> for the love of God, and the love of the Creatures cannot subsist together in one and the same Subject, but do mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually expell each other out of the heart of Man: <hi>For if any Man love the World, the love of the Father is not in him,</hi> as St. <hi>John</hi> affirmeth, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.15. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause God requires that the Heart of Man be offer'd unto
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:205288:24"/>him whole and entire; <hi>My Son</hi> (saith he) <hi>give me thy heart,</hi> Prov. 23, 26. Nor can he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a Rival with him in Man's Love; as soon as Man admits new and strange loves into his Heart, God forsakes it as polluted and defiled. But such is the Good will and Mercy of God in Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus towards straying Man, that no sooner, is the heart of Man offered unto him pure and void of the Love of the Creatures, but as soon he is willing to re-enter and dwell in it, and to fill it with divine Light and Joy. And to this mean of recovering the Love of God, do all those
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:205288:25"/>Precepts of Religion belong which forbid to <hi>love, covet,</hi> or <hi>seek after,</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> its <hi>Riches, Honours, Pleasures,</hi> or any created Thing.</p>
               <p>§. 14. Again, as in order to he recovery of the <hi>Love of God,</hi> the love of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures must be laid aside; so likewise, that Man may be freed from this love of the Creatures, it is needful that he abstain as much as may be, from the <hi>Converse and Ʋse of the Creatures,</hi> those especially that are grateful and pleasing to the Flesh: For besides that it appears unjust and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable that Rebels, and Traytours should presume to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:205288:25"/>meddle with the Divertise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that were provided for dutiful and obedient Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; so unsteady and frail is Humane Nature fince it was depraved by Sin, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not view nor enjoy those de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, without being invei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled in their Love. And therefore it behoveth us in our Food, Cloathing, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means of Life, to rest contented with things neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, and industriously to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void such as be delightful.</p>
               <p>§. 15. That which makes this part of our Duty the more easie, is the Cursing of the Earth, and the deface<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of at least this sublu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:205288:26"/>World, which by the wise and just Providence of God was the Consequence of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fall; by reason of which, the World as it now is, differs as much from it self as it was before the Fall, as a vile Dungeon does, from a Royal and Magnificent Palace. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Corruption of the World, the Apostle speaks, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.20, 21, &amp; 22. where he says; <hi>The Creature was made subject to Vanity, not willingly:</hi> And that <hi>at last the Creature it self shall be delivered from the Bondage of Corruption.</hi> If Men be passionately in love
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:205288:26"/>with this wretched Carcass of a World! What would they have done, if they had seen and possest it in its primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Perfection of Splendour and Beauty?</p>
               <p>§. 16. Furthermore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause <hi>Self-love</hi> is no less an Enemy to the Love of God, than is that of the other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and does usually raise Trophies to it self upon the others Ruines, it must of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity be put off also; and to effectuate this, we must keep up a constant Warfare with our corrupt Nature, all whose <hi>Thoughts, Counsels</hi> and <hi>Desires</hi> are by the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict of God himself, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:205288:27"/>
                  <hi>only and continually Evil:</hi> whatever it desires must be denied it, and the things for which it hath an Aversion must be forc'd upon it. We must do nothing to gratifie it, but its Motions must still be resisted to the end, that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought into Subjection, may never more obstruct or retard the operations of God's Spirit renewing Man in the Heart. And because all these things are hard and grievous, and very unacceptable to our corrupt Nature, we will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be throughly enclin'd to put them in practice; until the Mind being duely affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a sorrowful Sense of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:205288:27"/>Sin, and of its own Misery do first groan under the burden thereof, and aspire after de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from it. And these means which serve to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish <hi>the love of the Creatures in the Hearts of Men,</hi> are the same which Christ and his Apostles do so frequently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcate to us in the holy Scriptures, when they enjoin us <hi>Repentance, Self-denial, Renouncing the World, Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the Flesh, Taking up of the Cross, and putting off the Old man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 17. Moreover, as it is only the <hi>Gracious</hi> and <hi>imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate presence of the Deity,</hi> filling the Soul with Light and Joy that can beget there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:205288:28"/>in the true Love of God, which is the perfection of all Religion: So the other means of Salvation that I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready nam'd, do spring from a higher and far more Noble Principle than our Nature. For seeing the Human Nature as it is depraved by Sin, is blind, and seeketh it self and its own advantages in all things, always and every where; and seeing the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of Religion, of which we are speaking, are most unpleasing and hateful unto it; it is evident that a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with them cannot be expected without the assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of <hi>Divine Grace.</hi> And
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:205288:28"/>that, both <hi>Internal,</hi> which acteth upon the Mind <hi>imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately,</hi> instructing, allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, perswading and exciting it; and also <hi>External,</hi> which worketh by the <hi>Mediation</hi> of the outward Senses: So that it is not without ground that the Apostle says: <hi>It is God that worketh in us both to will and to do.</hi> Phil. 2, 3. For the obtaining of this Mean which is only in God's Power, there is requir'd on our part conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Prayer, and a ready Compliance with the Inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of the Holy Ghost. <hi>Ask,</hi> saith our Lord Christ, <hi>and ye shall receive.</hi> Matth. 7, 7. and <hi>grieve not the Holy
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:205288:29"/>Spirit of God,</hi> saith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4, 30.</p>
               <p>§. 18. But inasmuch as the inward Manifestations of the Holy Ghost do require a calm and composed Mind; and the soft Whispers, the sweet and gentle Voice of the holy Spirit teaching and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monishing in the bottom of the Heart cannot be heard and observed by unregenerate Men, because of the obstre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous Noise, and din of blustring and tumultuating Passions and Lusts; therefor it became necessary to call in the assistance of a <hi>Gross</hi> and <hi>Corporeal</hi> way of teaching, such as might make its way
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:205288:29"/>to the Mind through the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Senses. For this reason God sent the <hi>Prophets</hi> (to whom he had first manifest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himself, partly by Visions represented to their Fancies, sometimes when they slept, and sometimes when they were awake, and partly by a Voice and outward Signs) that they might warn and admonish other Men in his Name, concerning those things that belong'd to their Salvation. And whereas from <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fall downwards, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind growing still worse, breaking out into divers kinds of Sins, and adding new Crimes to their old Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:205288:30"/>wandered still farther from God, it became expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that God should warn them of their Danger, by new Advertisements from time to time, and that he should multiply his Precepts according to the diversity of the Sins, whereby Men igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly and inconsiderately strayed from the way of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, until at length the Wickedness of Men being risen to an Extraordinary height, and the Revelations of the Prophets, not being able to put a stop thereunto, the only begotten <hi>Son of God</hi> in his great Love to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, putting on our mortal
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:205288:30"/>Nature with all its Infirmities (yet without Sin) vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safed to dwell among Men, that he might perfectly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct them in all that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd their Salvation, and in a frail and mortal Body, like that which we bear about with us, might lead such a Life, as is necessarily to be led by All who shall be saved: that so by a sensible Experiment, he might convince us that a Christian Life is not impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to our Frailty, when for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with the Aids of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Grace: And finally might lay down his Life for Expiating the Sins of Men.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:205288:31"/>
               <p>§. 19. Also, the whole Doctrine of Religion com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the Discourses and Deportment of Jesus Christ, together with the Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Prophets and the Apostles is recorded in the Scriptures as in publick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gisters; that by this means it might be far and near diffus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed throughout the World. The <hi>Scriptures</hi> therefore are necessary, that the Precepts of Religion, and the means of Salvation already nam'd, might be made known unto Men.</p>
               <p>§. 20. But these are not yet all the Expedients that God hath made use of, for rend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:205288:31"/>Man's return to his <hi>Love</hi> and his way to Salvation the more plain and easie. Tho' all that which Men are concern'd to know and practice in order to their Salvation, be so ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and plainly delivered in the Scriptures, that all who are desirous to learn them, may with a due Application, easily there discover them; Yet there be many who do not apply themselves to the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Scriptures; many who blinded with Prejudice, are slow to understand that which they do read; others are remiss and negligent in performing what they do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand; and even they who
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:205288:32"/>have begun to tread in the Paths of Life, do many times thro' inadvertency step aside, or by the Violence of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations are hurried away in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the way of Sin, and being once fall'n into it, do sleep securely in it. To remedy which Evils, these following Expedients were provided. <hi>Pastors</hi> were appointed, whose Office it is to instruct, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monish, reprove and console: <hi>Religious Societies</hi> of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, or <hi>Churches</hi> were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stituted as useful for this end, that Christians might be helpful to one another, in promoting the common work of their Salvation, by instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:205288:32"/>the Ignorant, reclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing such as do err from the Truth; raising up those that are cast down, quickning the lukewarm; rebuking those that commit Sin, and avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing such as be contumacious. <hi>Religious Assemblies</hi> also, <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick Worship and Sacraments</hi> were instituted, which tho' they do greatly contribute to the promoting of Christians in Faith and true Holiness, do yet notwithstanding manifest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly suppose <hi>Pastors</hi> and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Societies,</hi> and may be consider'd by us as Sanctions of those Laws whereby Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors and Churches are Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized, to which we must
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:205288:33"/>give obedience, or be depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the Benefit of Publick Worship, and of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the Sacraments. And last of all, to the end that the publick Affairs of every Church might be rightly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministred, that is, that every thing might be done decent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and in order, and that Communion might be kept up, and Peace and Concord <hi>maintain'd</hi> among the <hi>Churches, Church Government</hi> was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed.</p>
               <p>§. 21. Thus have I link by link turn'd over <hi>the whole Chain of Religion,</hi> beginning at the highest degree thereof, <hi>viz. THE LOVE OF GOD,</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:205288:33"/>which alone is sought and enjoin'd for it self, descending from this to the <hi>immediate Means</hi> whereby it is attain'd, and from them to such as be <hi>more remote,</hi> until at last we come to the <hi>most remote</hi> of all. This account, which I have given of Religion, furnishes us with a Key, whereby any one that is but indifferently vers'd in Theological Studies, may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily discover what place each part holds in the <hi>Systeme</hi> of Religion; how one Part stands related to such other Parts as are above, as a Mean to the End; and to such as are below it, as the End to the Means: and in what degree of necessity every part ought
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:205288:34"/>to be held. But for the sake of Beginners, I shall propose one or more of those things in this Scheme, that deserve the greatest Consideration.</p>
               <p>§. 22. The first is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Difference between <hi>Charity</hi> or the <hi>Love of God,</hi> and all the other Parts of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; among which it hath the pre-eminence, because it alone is desired for it self, and all the rest are instituted for its sake, that by their means and subserviency, Mankind, which was fall'n from the pure and chaste Love of God, into the strange and adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Love of the Creatures, may again be reduc'd to the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:205288:34"/>Love which they owe unto God. And thus Charity is related to the other Parts of Religion, as the End is to the Means: agreeable to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle's plain Instruction; <hi>The end of the Commandment is Charity.</hi> Eph. 4, 11. Now as the wooden Frames and Scaffolds that are used in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, are taken away when the work is ended, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then no longer useful; so when the <hi>Love of God</hi> shall be perfected in the hearts of those that are to be saved, then Sacraments, Pastours, Churches, the holy Scriptures, the renouncing of the World, the mortifying of the Flesh,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:205288:35"/>Repentance, Faith, and all the other Parts of Religion that are distinct from Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, shall cease: as the same Apostle teacheth us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13▪8. <hi>Charity,</hi> saith he, <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver faileth, but whether there be Prophecies, they shall fail; whether there be Tongues, they shall cease; whether there be Knowledge, it shall vanish a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; when that which is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect shall come; then that which is in part shall be done away: Now abideth Faith, Hope and Charity; but the greatest of these is Charity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 23. Another thing that is to be diligently observed in this Scheme, concerneth those
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:205288:35"/>Parts of Religion that are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct from Charity, their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference among themselves as they stand related to it as to their End. And in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, they are classed in a three-fold Difference. They are all means for recovering Charity. But (1.) Some of them are <hi>Necessary,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al <hi>Sure</hi> and <hi>Infallible:</hi> others (2.) are indeed <hi>Necessary</hi> but <hi>not Sure</hi> and <hi>Infallible:</hi> and others (3.) finally are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Sure</hi> and <hi>Infallible,</hi> nor <hi>absolutely</hi> and <hi>Indispensably Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary.</hi> In the <hi>first Rank</hi> are <hi>Faith in Jesus Christ</hi> the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, <hi>Repentance,</hi> the <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying of the Corrupt Nature,</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:205288:36"/>or <hi>the Old Man;</hi> the <hi>renounce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the World</hi> with all its Pomps and Vanities, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally the <hi>Weaning</hi> of the <hi>Heart</hi> from the impure Love of the World, and all the Creatures which being once rooted out, the Love of God succeeds and is kindled up and shed abroad in the Heart by the Holy Ghost. All these be <hi>indispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sably Necessary</hi> for recovering the Love of God, and they have a sure and infallible Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate or Immediate Connexion therewith. In the <hi>second Rank</hi> stand the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> which for Reasons already express'd are <hi>simply Necessary,</hi> that Men may attain to the knowledge
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:205288:36"/>of such things as it Concerns them to know and Practice, in order to their Salvation. Which nevertheless is not so to be understood, as if those who were once well acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Doctrine of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion delivered in the H. Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, could not afterwards live a Christian Life without those Sacred Books. For as <hi>Augustine</hi> writes in his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise of Christian Doctrine lib. 1. Ch. 39.
<q rend="margQuotes">A Man ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Faith, Hope and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and retaining them sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fastly, needs not the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, except it be for the Instruction of others.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:205288:37"/>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Thus by these three many live in the Desart without Books; whence I think that in them is fulfilled that say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>whether there be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesies they shall fail; or Tongues they shall Cease; or Knowledge, it shall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed,</hi> &amp;c.</q> But tho' the Scriptures be <hi>necessary</hi> in the degree I have mentioned, yet are they not <hi>sure</hi> and <hi>Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible</hi> means of Salvation: See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very many of those who have them, and read them daily, come short of it, not for any fault in the Scriptures, but in the Persons themselves who take no care to order their Lives and Manners according
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:205288:37"/>to the Prescripts in them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered.</p>
               <p>§. 24. In the <hi>third Rank</hi> of means of Salvation, which are neither <hi>necessary</hi> nor <hi>sure</hi> and <hi>Infallible,</hi> are included <hi>Pastors,</hi> Religious Societies, or <hi>Churches, Sacraments, Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worship, Ecclesiastical Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> or Church Discipline, and if there be any other Institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God for this End, that Men may be excited to learn, or keep in Mind, or Practice the Duties of Religion, that are fully and clearly delivered in the Scriptures. That these have no sure and infallible Connexion with the Salvation of Men, is more evident than
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:205288:38"/>to want either proof or Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration: And altho' Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians ought not to Neglect or Despise, but to make use of them when they can be had as well because they are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed by God, as that in the right use of them many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Advantages may be reaped; yet this will not make them absolutely and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dispensably necessary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, for it is certain that such as have the Scriptures, if they carefully and diligently peruse them, may both dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the way of Salvation mark'd out in them, and having found it, may begin to walk in it, and by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssistance
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:205288:38"/>of God's Grace, may constantly persevere therein, until at last they work out their Salvation, altho' they live in such a Corner of the World, where they have no Opportunities, either of Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers whom they may hear, or of Churches, to which they may join themselves, or (by consequence) of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, of which they may partake. Of this we have notable Instances in some of the Hermits, particularly in <hi>Paul</hi> the first of them, who having pass'd his whole time from his blooming Youth to an extream old Age, in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Desart, without the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:205288:39"/>Company or Society of any man, except <hi>Anthony</hi> alone, with whom he convers'd for a short time, and that not long before his Death, hath deservedly obtain'd a great Reputation for Piety in the Church of Christ.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:205288:39"/>
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>[Wherein several material Propositions and useful Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rollaries are deduced from the preceding Descriptions of this Theologie. How to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern betwixt the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Principles of Religion, and such as are not funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental; and betwixt dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, dangerous, and harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less Errors.]</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>§. 25. HAving laid down the General I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea of this Theology, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the more distinct and particular Explication
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:205288:40"/>thereof, I come now to the many and weighty Proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Rules, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusions which may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from this Doctrine. And indeed so various and manifold is the use of this <hi>Comparative Theologie</hi> (which I have already explain'd) both in a private Life, and also for the right ordering of the Church; it abounds with so many useful Rules and Instructions for every kind of Life, that it would be hard to reckon up all that might be deduced from it, by serions and attentive Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I shall instance only in a few for a Tryal.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:205288:40"/>
               <p>§. 26. First then by this Doctrine of <hi>Comparative Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> it plainly appears, that the <hi>Precepts of the Christian Religion</hi> have proceeded nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the mere <hi>Arbitrary Will</hi> of God, nor from his <hi>Wrath</hi> and <hi>Displeasure;</hi> but from <hi>Love, Favour,</hi> and <hi>Good will</hi> toward fall'n Man. And the Reason why God hath imposed the hard Laws of <hi>Repentance, Self-denial,</hi> and the <hi>Renouncing of the World,</hi> as necessary to be observed by all that would be saved, is not, that he might exercise his Authority over Men, or be aveng'd on them; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause there is no other safe and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:205288:41"/>secure way of raising them to a true and lasting Happiness, besides that which the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of Religion do prescribe. God might indeed by vertue of his Omnipotence have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored Man, who was fall'n into Sin and Misery, unto his original holy and happy State, without the Interven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a <hi>Medicinal Penitence.</hi> But recent experience and the notable instance of instabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and inconstancy, which <hi>Adam</hi> had given, do evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly discover that nothing was to be expected this way, but that <hi>Adam</hi> having lightly escaped so great a Danger, would have been the more presumptuous to offend again;
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:205288:41"/>or if his Experience had made him more cautious and wary, yet his Children would rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily have relapsed into his Sin and Misery. So that if this Method had been taken for recovering fall'n Man, its probable that <hi>Adam</hi> only would have been saved by it. For this reason it was more agreeable both to the Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Goodness of God, to grant unto fall'n Man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress and return unto his first State of Happiness by the way of <hi>Penitence</hi> only, which tho' it be the more difficult, yet is it the most safe and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible. For as those who come to great Fortunes, either by
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:205288:42"/>Succession to their Parents, or by the Bounty of their Prince, are more probably en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to squander away their Wealth, than others, who have acquir'd Riches by their own Industry and Labour, after they have felt the pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Difficulties of Want and Poverty: So it is not to be doubted, but those Men who have with Difficulty wrestled out of the deep Gulf of Sin and Misery, and have come to Happiness, by the rough, uneasy and narrow way of <hi>Penitence,</hi> will prove far more constant in the Love of their Creator, and more firm and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute in sustaining and répel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:205288:42"/>the assaults of Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, than was either <hi>Adam,</hi> who was created in a State of Felicity, or than his Poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity would have been, in case that Happiness had been by Succession transmitted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them from <hi>Adam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 27. If it shall here be enquired, might not God have restored man immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after his Fall, and having restored, confirmed him also in grace and holiness, and put him out of all danger of fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing again any more, so as he should not have been after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward obnoxious unto Sin, no more than the glorious An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels? I answer, that a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:205288:43"/>State of Grace and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness,</hi> is both the Fruit and Reward of a previous and tried Constancy and Firmness in the Love of God. That it was granted upon no other Conditions to the Angels, who persisted in their Duty and Fidelity, nor would have been given unto <hi>Adam,</hi> sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose he had not sinned, till after a competent time of Tryal faithfully spent in the Love of God: Finally, that it is not possible that a reason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Creature can attain to a consummated State of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection by any other way, without infringing its Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which God will have
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:205288:43"/>preserv'd safe and inviolate.</p>
               <p>[§. For such is the <hi>Nature of Liberty,</hi> that without hurt and prejudice to it self, it cannot allow, that any of the Faculties that are under its Conduct, especially the Will, should be determined by any other Principle than it self, in their application to this rather than the other suitable Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, after this, rather than the other manner. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless it will suffer it self to be sixed and bound either to good or evil by cords of its own making; such are the <hi>Habits</hi> contracted by long and continued Exercises of the Acts of Love, Desire,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:205288:44"/>Complacency, Enjoyment, and the like, upon the same Objects: whereby a Man finds himself push'd forward to the Love, Desire, and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of those Objects: and drawn back when he offers to separate and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw his Affections from them; so that without Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty and Violence done to himself, he cannot abstain from the Acts unto which such Habits do dispose him, no more than exercise thecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; which hath given the rise to that vulgar Maxim <hi>Custom is a second Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. This is plain and unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable in the Case of Evil
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:205288:44"/>Habits that are so common and ordinary. For who knows not that a Glutton, a Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, or a Lascivious Person, for Example, are so enslaved to those vicious Habits and Lusts which they serve, that they cannot without great Difficulty and much strug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, refrain from satiating their sensual Desires and Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, when they have it in their Power, nor be reclaimed from their dissolute Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation, to a Sober, a Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and a chaste Conversati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> doth significantly express, when he saith, <hi>Can the Aethi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opian change his Colour, or the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:205288:45"/>Leopard his Spots. Then may ye also do good, who are accustom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do evil.</hi> Jer. 13.23.</p>
               <p>§. Nor is there less force and efficacy in <hi>Good Habits,</hi> which are contracted by a long course of good Actions perform'd by the Power of the Holy Ghost, whereby the old man is subdued and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, the new, quickned and advanced by degrees, till in the end he become a perfect Man. For when any Person is once come this length, he becomes ready, forward and inclin'd to Good; slow, back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and averse to Evil. As St. <hi>John</hi> instructs us. <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever is born of God doth not
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:205288:45"/>commit Sin, for the seed of God abideth in him, and he cannot sin because he is horn of God.</hi> 1 Joh. 3.9. To this the Experience also of the Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate, who declare that they find it so, doth perfectly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</p>
               <p>§. After that these good or evil Habits have received their proper and suitable im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements from God, that is, after he has fortified and established the good, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed measures and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications of his Grace; and has plyed the Evil with repeated endeavours, and all to no purpose, to reclaim them, when he resolves that
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:205288:46"/>the Graces of his Spirit shall not be any more prostituted to the Scorn and Contempt of thos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ooted in Sin; and when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> rewards the Godly for the good use that they have made of their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, with plentiful mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures of Grace, and takes the Government of their free will (after they have freely resign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it) into his own hands: then follows the final, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable and endless Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duration of the wicked in sin, and the establishment of the Godly in Grace and Holiness. Whence it appears, that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional free Creatures can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be establish'd in a State
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:205288:46"/>of Grace, nor hardened into a State of Sin, without infring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Liberty, except the free use and exercise thereof in Good or Evil (which in good at least must be habitual) have gone before it.]</p>
               <p>§. 28. Secondly, This Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Comparative Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie</hi> discovers the ground of that which the Apostle deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. where he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares that those Parts of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which are commonly most esteemed, such are, much knowledge in divine Things, Orthodoxy, Faith and suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Persecution for the true Religion even unto
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:205288:47"/>death) will be improfitable to Salvation without <hi>Charity;</hi> because these and all other things pertaining to Religion, are for this end ordain'd and enjoin'd by God, that by them Men may be brought to <hi>Charity</hi> or the Love of God; so that if they do not attain to that end, they become vain and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable. Wherefor they are far deceiv'd who conceive good hopes, and entertain a good Opinion of themselves, and of their own Spiritual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, because they do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to this, or the other Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Christians, because they are diligent and assiduous, in Hearing, Reading, Praying
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:205288:47"/>and Communicating; all these being too weak Supporters whereupon to build a solid Hope of Salvation. For, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less Men will denounce War against their corrupt Nature, renounce the World and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny themselves, they shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver recover the <hi>True and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Love of God;</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the unfeigned <hi>Love of God,</hi> they shall never come to his Presence, nor to the Dwelling-place of the Blessed.</p>
               <p>§. 29. Thirdly, This Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy teacheth us, how to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish between the <hi>Essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial</hi> or <hi>Fundamental Principles</hi> of Religion, and those that
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:205288:48"/>are <hi>not fundamental.</hi> And here I take the Essence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion not strictly, for all that which belongeth to Religion always, and in all States (in which sense the <hi>Love of God</hi> alone makes up the whole Essence of Religion) but more largely for all those things which are necessary for Men, considered in a State of corrupt Nature, that they may be fitted for and brought into the Enjoyment of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Happiness. Now where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as some parts of Religion, are means of Salvation, both necessary; and sure or infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, others necessary, but not sure; and others are indeed
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:205288:48"/>means of Salvation, but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sure nor necessary; it is evident that the Precepts and Institutions of the third Class do by no means belong to the Tribe of the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals of Religion. Moreover, because a fundamental of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion properly so called, is, that the Knowledge whereof is necessary to Salvation di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, and of it self; and all the Precepts and Institutions of the first Class, and they only are such; from this, it does appear that the whole Family of the <hi>Fundamentals</hi> of Religion is contain'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Limits of the first Class. But because Men can
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:205288:49"/>by no other means come to the certain Knowledge of the Fundamentals of Religion, than by the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for to know the Scriptures and to acknowledge them for a sure and infallible Rule of Faith, may be call'd a <hi>secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary Fundamental</hi> Principle of Religion.</p>
               <p>§. 30. Fourthly, This Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy teacheth also the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of <hi>Errors;</hi> that some are <hi>damnable</hi> and <hi>pernicious;</hi> some <hi>dangerous</hi> only, and some <hi>harmless:</hi> All those Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors touching Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which do necessarily subvert some <hi>Fundamental</hi> principle of Religion, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:205288:49"/>that in the Opinion and Judgment of the erring Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, or that cannot sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist at the same time, and in the same Mind with the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the Fundamental Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Religion. These and these only are to be look'd upon as <hi>destructive</hi> and <hi>damnable,</hi> and as such, are with great Care and Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to be expell'd out of the Confines of the Church. For the Christian Religion is like a Bridge by which alone Men can go from this Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of Miseries to the blessed Regions of Light and Peace; and the <hi>fundamental Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> of Religion are as so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:205288:50"/>Arches, which join'd and united together, do make up this Bridge, and therefore those Errors that do overturn any of the fundamental Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Religion, do as it were, cut out an Arch from the Bridge, whereby a Breach is made in it, and the Passage by it into Heaven is thus cut off and obstructed.</p>
               <p>§. 31. Again those <hi>Errors</hi> are to be avoided as <hi>dangerous,</hi> whose tendency is to make Men remiss and negligent in the business of their Salvation: of this kind is that Error a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed to <hi>Origen,</hi> concerning the <hi>Punishment of the Devils and Damned.</hi> That after a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:205288:50"/>long course of time they shall come to an End, and that the Damned themselves shall at last be translated into the Habitations of the Blessed. By which Doctrine, it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that the fear of Hell, and the force thereof to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strain Men from Sin, is in great measure weakned and infringed. Finally, those Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors may be tolerated as <hi>harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less,</hi> whereby a Christian who is in the way of Salvation, is neither lett nor retarded in his course, such was the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> concerning the <hi>Rebaptization of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks;</hi> and another of <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> who writes that our Saviour
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:205288:51"/>was fifty years old when he suffered.</p>
               <p>§. 32. From hence in the 5th place we may draw <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Principles,</hi> for directing not only private Christians, how far they may entertain or refuse <hi>External Communion</hi> with the different, yea ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse Sects and Societies of Christians into which the Unity of the Christian Church is miserably divided and rent asunder: But Church Governours also in the making and abrogating Ecclesiastical Laws. For, whereas the End and Design of those Christian Societies, which we call Churches, is,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:205288:51"/>that by their Help, every private Christian may be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded in a Course of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and assisted in working out their Salvation: It is plain; <hi>First,</hi> That a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, who lays the work of his Salvation to heart, ought (if his Circumstances will permit him) to join himself unto, and associate with those Churches, wherein the best helps to Piety are to be found. Next, that he must abstain from the Communion of those Churches, whose Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowship is apt to hinder or retard his Progress in true Piety, either because the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Christian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:205288:52"/>is therein corrupted with evil Principles, and such as flatter corrupt Nature, or because the Force and Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy of sound and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some Doctrine is impair'd and enervated, by the mischiev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Examples of a worldly Life; or finally, because the Priviledge of Communion is annexed to something that is unlawful, as a necessary Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That the Communion of that Church whereof he is a Member al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and whose Fellowship, tho' it be little useful to Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet is not prejudicial to it, should be continued in, in case it cannot be forsaken
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:205288:52"/>without some great Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience.</p>
               <p>§. 33. For the same reason also it becomes the Duty of all those who are promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Government of Churches to make use of their Power and Authority for <hi>Edification,</hi> and not for <hi>Destruction,</hi> not enjoining any thing that is not conducive to Christians, their Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in true Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring any thing as a neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary Condition of External Communion, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Person in his right Mind, and who is acted by a serious and sincere Desire, after Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness, cannot perform with a
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:205288:53"/>good Conscience; lest they chance to debar from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Communion of their Church, those whom Christ hath honour'd with inward and Spiritual Communion with himself, and with the Saints, that is, with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visible Church. And finally, constraining no Persons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their Mind and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, to an external Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with any Church.</p>
               <p>[§. In this Corrolary we may behold, as in a Glass, <hi>The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorble State of the Christian World</hi> at this Day, wherein almost every Sect of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, at least the Ruling Part among them, do require the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:205288:53"/>Belief and Profession of their peculiar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and distinguishing Doctrines, which are some of them obscure, others doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and incertain, and others false, as a necessary Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Communion, sowing by this means the Seeds of Discord, and Division, and Hatred among Christians, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of that Unity, and Love, and Concord, which our Saviour so earnestly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to his Disciples. Nor is this all, but they do what in them lies to force all others, by Mulcts, Banish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Corporal Punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to embrace their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and to fulfil the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:205288:54"/>Conditions thereof; and by so doing, instead of making Men Christians, they only make them Hypocrites; of all Sinners the most hateful in the sight of God.]</p>
               <p>§. 34. Last of all, from this Scheme of <hi>Comparative Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie,</hi> it does plainly appear, that <hi>Church Government</hi> is such a Mean of recovering the Love of God, as is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther necessary, nor sure and infallible, and consequently, that it is not a <hi>Fundamental Principle,</hi> nor an Essential Member of the Christian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; and that in the Body thereof, it holds the Place, not of the Heart or other Vitals,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:205288:54"/>but of the more extream Parts. This is a Matter that ought to be well considered by all Christians, but especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by those among whom bitter Envyings, and Strifes, and Contentions are kept up, Discord and Tumults are rais<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Animosities and Hatred are exercised about <hi>particular Forms of Church Government and Discipline,</hi> to the great Reproach of Christianity, the Scandal of the Weak, and the woeful Decay, or (shall I say) the utter Ruin and Subversion of true Piety. How much better were it, and more conducive to the Honour of the Christian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:205288:55"/>to Piety and to Peace, that Christians should rather exercise a mutual Forbearance in this Case, by allowing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one free Liberty to think, and speak, and act as they please, in these and other such like Matters that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from the Center of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, concerning which, sincere Lovers of Truth and Holiness may differ in their Judgments, and that without any prejudice to mutual Love and the Duties of Charity, either among single Persons, or among the Societies of Christians and Churches.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:205288:55"/>
               <head>[The Conclusion,</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Wherein the use of this Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie is more particularly declared. The Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency to which they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, who are not acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it. The Character of one who follows its dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. The Epilogue.]</p>
               </argument>
               <p>[§. FRom all that has been said, the notable use and necessity of this <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Theologie</hi> does abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly appear; For he who does not understand the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and differing respects
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:205288:56"/>and relations of the several parts of Religion among themselves (which this Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy teaches) cannot but of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten stumble and fall, and wander in his way to eternal Life. For either,</p>
               <p>§. <hi>First,</hi> he will consider all the Parts of Religion as Equal, and standing upon the same Level, and so will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply himself to them indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently without Order or Choice, practising now one Duty, then another, as his Inclinations or Circumstances shall prompt him: not unlike to an unskilful Husbandman, that should take much Pains in Sowing, Digging, Tilling,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:205288:56"/>Harrowing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> his Ground, without any regard to the Order or Season that ought to be observed therein; for as this Man would unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly fall short of the hoped for Reward of his Labours, I mean, of a plentiful Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest; so the other would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly lose the Fruit and Reward of a Religious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation, <hi>viz.</hi> Regeneration and Eternal Life. Now I make no doubt but there are many such to be found among the Professors of Christianity, who considering only what is common to all the Parts and Precepts of their Religion, <hi>viz.</hi> The stamp of Divine
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:205288:57"/>Authority, and not advert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the proper and pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Aims of every one of them in particular, do keep a mighty Stir, and are much taken up about Religion to little purpose, without mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any considerable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress in it; like the Men of <hi>Sodom,</hi> who <hi>being smitten with Blindness, wearied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in vain,</hi> to find the Door of <hi>Lot</hi>'s House, and seem to be pointed out by the Apostle under the figure of <hi>silly Women, who are ever learning, and never able to come to the</hi> (saving and Practical) <hi>Knowledge of the Truth.</hi> Or,</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:205288:57"/>
               <p>§. <hi>Secondly,</hi> He will prefer the <hi>lesser</hi> and <hi>lighter</hi> Matters of Religion, to such as be <hi>greater</hi> and <hi>more weighty:</hi> with which our Saviour up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braids the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sees, who <hi>paid Tythes</hi> of <hi>Mint, Cummin and Anise,</hi> but <hi>neglected the weightier things of the Law, Judgment, Mercy and Truth.</hi> A fault whereof the greater part of Christians are guilty, who put a greater Value upon a <hi>right Belief and Perswasion</hi> touching things <hi>less necessary,</hi> such as are almost all the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguishing Doctrines of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Sect of Christians, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with some Religious
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:205288:58"/>Rites and particular Rules and Forms of Church Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and Government, much controverted in these Times, concerning which, a Man may think and act thus, or otherwise (provided he act not against his Conscience) without prejudice to his Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, than they do upon <hi>Holiness of Heart and Life,</hi> without which, no man shall see God. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14, being less sollicitous for this than the other. For as in their own Practice, they study more to be <hi>Orthodox,</hi> than to be <hi>Humble, Charitable, Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified to the World and Self-denied;</hi>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:205288:58"/>so they do with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Arms receive into their Communion all that do agree with them in Doctrine and Worship, be their Lives ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so sensual and worldly, but do exclude as Aliens and Strangers, all such as differ from them, in these Matters, be their Lives otherwise never so harmless and holy, seeking rather to gain Disciples and Followers to their own way and party, than to Christ and his Religion; who, if with the Proselytes of the Scribes and Pharisees they grow not worse, yet will certainly get little more by their Change, than an exchange of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:205288:59"/>and of the Modes and Circumstances of External Worship.</p>
               <p>§. They do also split upon this same Rock, who, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting the Capital Vertues of the Christain Religion, take up their rest in the means subservient thereunto, such as are the Scriptures, Sermons, Sacraments, and the like (whose use is to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struct Men in the essential Duties of Religion, to stir them up to, and assist them in the performance of them) in which we may observe many to be much employed, who do think that in so do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they have reasonably
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:205288:59"/>well discharged their Duty as Christians, tho' they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver aspire after <hi>Humility,</hi> the <hi>Mortification of the Flesh,</hi> the <hi>renouncing of the World,</hi> and the Love of God and their Neighbour, for the sake of which, all those other things wherewith they are so much taken up, were purely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended and appointed: not a whit wiser than one who intending a Journey to some remote Country or City, should Employ all his Time and Care in providing and viewing of Horses, Chariots, Servants, Provisions and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Necessaries for a Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and in the mean time,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:205288:60"/>never stir a foot from Home, to set forward on the Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Or,</p>
               <p>§. They will Slight and Neglect the <hi>Inferiour Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>string</hi> and <hi>subservient Parts and Duties</hi> of Religion, and seek to come at those of the highest Rank and Degree without them: with no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Success, than if a Man should endeavour to get up to the top of a high Tower without the help of the Stairs, that lead to it, by throwing out his Arms, straining his Body and standing on tip-toe. And this fault is but too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon among Christians, who imagine they can attain to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:205288:60"/>
                  <hi>Internalvertues</hi> of Contrition, Humility, Contempt of the World, Self-denial, the Love of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by Meditation and thinking only, without Practising the External good Works that dispose and lead thereunto, and without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding the Allurements and Temptations to the contrary Vices, such as be Riches, Honours, Pleasures, and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>millarity and Friendship of worldly-minded-Men: acting in this with as little Colour of Reason, as one, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing shut up in a dark Prison or plunged in Snow up to the Chin, should expect to be enlightned and warmed
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:205288:61"/>by the mere force of his Imagination, without come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth into the bright and warm Sun.</p>
               <p>To these we may add some others, who boast of inward Manifestations of the Spirit, Commnion with God, Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Joys, and such like Rewards and Comforts of a pure Heart, altho' they have not as yet purged out the old leaven of Carnal Lusts, and Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Affections, embracing thus the Shadow for the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance.</p>
               <p>§. On the Contrary, he who is Acquainted with the Doctrine of this Pure and Peaceable <hi>Theologie,</hi> and will
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:205288:61"/>chuse to follow its Directions, he considers <hi>Charity</hi> or the <hi>Love of God,</hi> as the great <hi>End,</hi> and the other <hi>Duties</hi> and <hi>Vertues</hi> belonging to the Christian Religion as the <hi>Means</hi> appointed for attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereunto: And accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, he makes the first his great Aim and Business, and the rest he regardeth and useth only in Consideration of their subserviency to this first. He reads the Scriptures, Meditates, hears Sermons, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the Sacraments, and performs other subservient Duties of Religion, not that he may rest in them, but that by their means he may be
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:205288:62"/>stirred up and helped for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the contempt of himself and the World, and to the love of God, and of his Neighbour for God's sake. Knowing that all the Labour that's laid out that way is lost, if it do not Contribute to this End. And as, tho' Eating and Drinking are the necessary Means of Life and Health, and yet Men must not be always Eating and Drinking, but must allow some time for Digestion; so he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serves a Mediocrity in Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures, hearing Sermons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> avoiding Excess therein as hurtful.</p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:205288:62"/>
               <p>§. There is no help to Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, how mean and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible soever it may appear which he either contemns in his own Practice, or condemns in anothers, yet is he not so much wedded to any Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Means of Salvation, which are not necessary, but that he can lay them aside, in case that through long use, or rather abuse, they are become improfitable or hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, as was the Brazen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; he is neither so fond nor so afraid of any Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Rite or Ceremony, or Ecclesiastical Custom that is Innocent, and being indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in it self, may be used
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:205288:63"/>for a good End, but he can either use or abstain from it as the Peace of the Church, or the edification of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour does require herein, imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taing the Apostle, who <hi>To the Jews became as a Jew, that he might gain the Jews; to them that were under the Law, as under the Law, that he might gain them that were under the Law; to them who were without the Law as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Law, that he might gain them that were without Law; to the weak he became as weak, that he might gain the weak, finally he was made all things unto all Men, that he might by all means save some.</hi> 1 Cor. 9.20, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:205288:63"/>
               <p>§. The <hi>Necessary Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Truths</hi> of Religion, he finds to be but few, to which he firmly adheres, and lays them up carefully in his Heart, but is less taken up with the rest, concerning which he loves not to debate with any person, well knowing, that as few Controversies were ever ended this way, so the Minds of Men are thereby diverted from the Study of Holiness, and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, Animosities, Divisions, and Persecutions are begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and fomented; and that a further Progress and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement in the saving knowledge of the Truth, is
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:205288:64"/>better attain'd by holy living, than by much Disputing; he maintains an inward spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Communion of Love and Affection with all that truly fear God, and sincerely seek him; however much they may differ from him, and among themselves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that are less necessary: being ready to entertain ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Communion with 'em, so far as the Terms and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of external Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which they require, will allow, and so far as they do not obstruct the Love of God, and the Mortifying of our corrupt Nature: but care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:205288:64"/>avoids the Company and Familiarity of all wicked and worldly-minded Men, as hurtful and contagious, altho' they agree with him in the Profession of the same Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and outward Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship.]</p>
               <p>§. 35. These inferences ought to have been treated with more accuracy and at greater length, but the short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the time allotted for this Exercise, hath obliged me to abridge them, and si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently to pass over others of some consequence. Besides, I'm afraid my Hearers may already be weary of this Discourse, which the great
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:205288:65"/>variety of Matter, that of necessity must be crowded in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to its narrow bounds hath rendred more profitable than pleasant. And therefore I shall here put a stop to it, heartily recommending the Heads of it to you, <hi>my dear Fellow-Students,</hi> to be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther digested, amplified and enlarged by you, in your more retir'd Thoughts and private Meditations: And to the Father of Lights, to be by Him plentifully watered with the Blessing of Heaven.</p>
               <p>To the All-Good, All-Wise, and All-Mighty Lord our God, Father, Son, and and Holy Spirit, be Praise and Glory for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:205288:65"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>